RG 030, Council of Defense
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut State Council of Defense records
1917-1919
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut State Council of Defense
198 cubic feet
The Council of Defense coordinated war activities in Connecticut during World War I. Its various committees dealt with the various areas of concern, such as food supply, fuel conservation, transportation, military and naval affairs and publicity.
RG030
T001102
Historical Note
The Council of Defense was Connecticut's agency for coordinating its war activities during World War I. Appointed on 26 April 1917 by Gov. Marcus Holcomb under the authority of the emergency act (Chap. 44, Public Acts of 1917), it initially consisted of eleven members representing industry, labor, the professions and the military, with Richard M. Bissell as Chairman.1 The first meeting was held on 8 May 1917 and the agency was discontinued in March 1919.
At first the Council was organized in a series of appointed committees to deal with the various areas of concern, such as food supply, fuel conservation, transportation, military and naval affairs and publicity. A small secretarial and administrative staff was headed by Thomas Hewes. As the work expanded, a number of the committees acquired their own full-time staffs and became "Departments", and a stronger executive control was established through the creation of an Executive Department headed by Joseph M. Alsop, a member of the Council.
Much of the Council's attention was devoted to coordinating, supporting and publicizing the work of other agencies. Leading officials of many other war agencies served also on Council of Defense committees, and in some cases the Council supplied staff assistance and other help to United States agencies in Connecticut or to other Connecticut agencies in the war effort. The Military Census, which was the first Connecticut war agency (Feb.. 7, 1917), was represented on the Council by its director, and the Committee on Food Supply, which preceded the Council by a couple of weeks, became one of its departments. The Council collaborated closely with the United States Food Administration, the United States Fuel Administration, the United States Employment Service, the Committee on Public Information and, of course, the Council of National Defense. Efforts were made to organize town "war bureaux" to coordinate war work on a local scale; these met with varying success and little record of their work survives. Auxiliary committees on the county level also existed; the files of the New London one are here.
Mention must be made of the important Woman's Division. Organized first as a state committee of the Council of National Defense Woman's Committee, it gradually, by the summer of 1918, assumed the status of a department in the Connecticut Council. As that occurred, some of its earlier programs (Americanization, child welfare, "commercial economy", etc.) were taken over by other units of the Council, but the Woman's Division continued to be represented on those committees and to play an important role in all the agency's work.
Endnotes
1The appointment document is in RG 005:022 Office of the Governor, Marcus H. Holcomb, 1917-1918, file 107. Other background material is in the same series, files 104, 105, and 137. The official history, prepared by Henry M. Wriston and others, is
Report of the Connecticut State Council of Defense, December 1918 (Hartford, 1919 ).
Scope and Content
The record group contains general records as well as records from the following departments: Executive, Americanization, Child Welfare, Food Supply, Fuel Conservation, Health and Recreation, Historical Records, Military and Naval Committee, Publicity, Soldiers' and Sailors' Information Bureau, Transportation, Fund Raising, Woman's Division, and the New London Auxiliary Committee.
Arrangement
Series 1. General
Series 2. Executive Department
Series 3. Americanization department
Series 4. Child Welfare Department
Series 5. Food Supply Department
Series 6. Fuel Conservation Committee
Series 7. Health and Recreation Department
Series 8. Historical Records Department
Series 9. Military and Naval Committee
Series 10. Publicity Department
Series 11. Soldiers' and Sailors' Information Bureau
Series 12. Transportation Department
Series 13. Fund-Raising Activities
Series 14. Woman's Division
Series 15. New London county Auxiliary Committee
Series 16. Exhibit Material
Series 17. Miscellaneous
Related Material
RG 005:022, Office of the Governor, Marcus H. Holcomb, 1915-1921. See particularly, for 1917-1919, files 104, 105, 107, 137, and for 1919-1921, file 66.
RG 012, Connecticut State Library. Records of the War Records Department include much material closely related to records of the Historical Records Department of the Council of Defense. Also see War LIbrary Fund records, 1917.
RG 013, Military Department. Military Emergency Board orders pertaining to the Home Guard and the State Guard.
RG 018, Civil Service Commission. These materials, 1913-1921, were evidently held at one time by the War Records Department; they are related to the Military Census records (recruitment of nurses, etc.) and the Labor Department, Employment Service (placement of returned veterans).
RG 020, Department of Labor. Included are files of the U.S. Employment Service pertaining to the efforts to find jobs for demobilized service people.
RG 029, Military Census. This was in a sense the predecessor of the Council of Defense; its head became a COuncil member and records include material on draft age men, aliens, farms, crops, livestock, automobiles, doctors, nurses, and factories. Council of Defense Industrial Survey records are here.
RG 050, War Council. This was the World War II agency similar to the Council of Defense.
RG 064, Pictorial Collection. Included are a scattering of photographs and posters from the Council of Defense and war-related activities.
RG 069, Manuscript Collections. Some war-related groups include RG 069:001 (Hohenthal papers on draft board and temperance work), RG 069:002 (Crocker photographs of war-time Hartford), RG 06:017 (Lorenz photograph collection of prominent persons).
There are also several small record groups containing records of veterans' organizations.
Among the Classified Archives are personal papers and other materials pertaining to Connecticut in World War I. Most are catalogued under "European War, 1914-1918".
Separated Material
Exhibit and demonstration material.
The following items were transferred to the Museum of Connecticut History. These items were used to attract public attention and support or to explain and illustrate Council of Defense activities and war programs. It has not always been determined just how and where they were used. Most are damaged and extremely dirty. The following is a list of partial captions or descriptions.
1. The proportions of the problem in the United States - in Connecticut (incomplete). 2 panels, each 48 x 72 in.
2. The solution of the problem. 48 x 72 in.
3. True Americanism. 48 x 72 in.
4. Americanization - What it is, 48 x 782 in.
5. Connecticut is making good Governor's pledge to Pres. Wilson...Are you doing your part?. Wood frame. 48 x 108 in.
6. Dates you should remember...hasten the day of victory. Wood frame. 48 x 108 in.
7. War education and information - The Department of Publicity. Wood frame. 48 x 108 in.
8. Over the top (4th Liberty Loan). 48 x 108 in.
9. Millions for defense (4th Liberty Loan). Wood frame. 48 x 120 in.
10-12. Official U.S. Government war photographs. Three panels, each with mounted 8 x 10 in. glossy prints of military scenes, with typed captions. 2 panels, 48 x 96 in.; 1 panel 48 x 84 in.
13. Where Allied armies are smashing Huns. Wood frame. 48 x 108 in.
14. Where armies of democracy are smashing road to victory. Double panel, hinged. Wood frame. Each panel, 48 x 96 in.
15. Rallies carry war message to many thousands. Wood frame. 48 x 84 in.
16. Patriotic press of Connecticut backs up the republic. 42 x 84 in.
17. These Connecticut newspapers are helping win the war (mounted masthead clippings). Wood frame. 42 x 84 in.
18. Map of markets to which Pocahontas and New River coals are limited...1915. 40 x 60 in.
19. Emergency organization for the City of New Haven. Wood frame. 28 x 44 in.
20. Local agencies of the Connecticut State Council of Defense (map with colored buttons). Wood frame.
21. State Highway Department map with unidentified route markings. 26 x 36 in.
22. New England Fuel administration chart. 15 x 28 in.
23. Tell it to Pershing. 30 x 42 in.
24. New consecration is the duty of the living. 28 x 40 in.
25. Stand fast America! 28 x 40 in.
26. Large banner, approximately 8 x 20 feet, containing a representation of governor Holcomb's cable of support to President Wilson on 3(?) or 5 February 1917 has been destroyed. It appears in the photographs in Series 16, Exhibit Material and color photographs are in the Pictorial Collection (RG 064).
27. State of Connecticut Victory Liberty Loan Honor ROll. 48 x 60 in.
28. Some of the Publications issued by the Dept. of Publicity... Wood frame, glass. 32.5 x 40 in.
29. Make a Will (YMCA poster). 22 x 28 in.
30. Invest Wisely (YMCA poster). 22 x 28 in.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut State Council of Defense
Organizations:
Bissell, Richard M. (Richard Mervin), 1862-1941
Subjects:
Americanization; Connecticut -- History -- World War, 1914-1918; Connecticut State Council of Defense -- Records and correspondence; Food conservation; Food supply -- Connecticut; Fuel -- Conservation -- Connecticut; Fund raising -- Connecticut; World War, 1914-1918 -- Connecticut; World War, 1914-1918 -- Exhibitions -- Connecticut; World War, 1914-1918 -- Finance -- Connecticut; World War, 1914-1918 -- Food supply -- Connecticut; World War, 1914-1918 -- Fuel supplies -- Connecticut; World War, 1914-1918 -- Transportation -- Connecticut; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women -- Connecticut; World War, 1914-1918 -- United States -- Propaganda
Document Types:
Bills (legislative records); Broadsides; Card indexes; Clippings; Correspondence; Lantern slides; Lists; Metal cuts; Minutes; Pamphlets; Photographs; Posters; Press releases; Printing plates; Questionnaires; Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
Because of the physical problems involved, special arrangements must be made for the consultation of the lantern slides, and cuts and plates.
See the policy.
Provenance
When the war ended, the Council of Defense wound up its own activities. The committees were disbanded, most of the staff turned to other work, and the records were turned over to the State Library for preservation. The records became the responsibility of the War Records Department of the State Library, which was the successor to the Historical Records Department (headed by George Godard, the State Librarian) of the Council of Defense.
Container List
- Series 1. General
  - 1. Classified file, 1917-1919
    The general file, containing letters, memoranda, releases, publications and other materials. A copy of the classification scheme is available at the History and Genealogy reference desk.
    - A. Council of National Defense, Washington, D.C. (Box 1)
      - A01: Organization (including personnel) (Box 1)
      - A05: List of Bulletins of Council of National Defense (Box 1)
      - A05: Bulletins of Council of National Defense 1-105 (Box 1)
      - A05f: Bulletins of Field Division, Council of National Defense (Box 1)
      - A05.1: General Letters of Council of National Defense (Box 2)
      - A05.11: General Letters of Field Division (Box 2)
      - A05.14: Information Circulars of Council of National Defense (Box 2)
      - A05.16: National Defense Magazine (Box 3)
      - A05.2: News Articles (Box 3)
      - A07: Addresses at Conferences (Box 3)
      - A16: Method of Handling Mail (Box 3)
      - A100: Field Division, Council of National Defense (Box 3)
      - A101: Amalgamation of Work of Men and Women (Box 3)
      - A110: Mr. Alsop’s Correspondence as Federal Field Secretary for Connecticut Council of National Defense (Box 3)
    - C. State Council of Defense, Committees of State Council (Box 3)
      - C01: Organization, Personnel, etc. of Conn. Council (Box 3)
      - C04: Conn. Laws (Box 3)
      - Pamphlets (Box 3)
        - Congressional Record, 1917 July 13 (Box 3)
        - “Readjustment and Reconstruction Information” - Council of National Defense, 1919 (Box 3)
      - C05: Connecticut State Council - Activities (Box 4)
      - C05: Connecticut Bulletin (Box 4)
      - C05: Material About Connecticut Bulletin (Mailing Lists, Circulation, etc.) (Box 4)
      - C05: Connecticut Bulletin, Editorials for (Correspondence Re Editorials for Conn. Bulletins) (Box 4)
      - C06: Minutes of Council Meetings, 1917 May-December (Box 4)
      - C06: Minutes of Council Meetings, 1918 January-July (Box 5)
      - C06: Memoranda For Council Meetings (Box 6)
      - C06: Index of Council Meetings (Box 6)
      - C06.01: Procedure at Council Meetings - (Time of Meeting, etc.) (Box 6)
      - C06.1: Invitations to Edward's Dinner, 1917 June 13 (Box 6)
      - C06.2: Meeting at Capitol, 1917 November 19 (Box 6)
      - C06.3: List of People Who Attended Jan 1918 Convention (Box 7)
      - C06.3: Hearings of Convention [Transcript.], 1918 January (Box 7)
      - C06.3: Convention - [Letters Re], 1918 January (Box 7)
      - C06.4: War Conference, 1918 May 11 (Box 7)
      - C06.4: Requests For Tickets For War Conference, 1918 May 11 (Box 7)
      - C09: Questionnaires of Council of National Defense (Box 7)
      - C09: Conn. State Council of Defense - Reports To Mr. Guilford, 1917 June-1918 July (Box 7)
      - C09.b: Individual Reports Submitted For Mr. Wriston’s Report (filed by subject) (Box 8)
      - C09.r: [Correspondence Re Reports] (Box 8)
      - C09.w: Original Official Copies of Report - Draft of Mr. Wriston’s Report (Box 8)
      - C09.1: Method of Preparing Reports (Box 8)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council, Committee on Women’s Activities Reports (Box 8)
      - C10: Council National Defense - Reports (Final Report), 1918 April-December (Box 8)
      - C10: Connecticut Council of Defense, Employment Service Committee - Report (Box 9)
      - C10: Connecticut Council of Defense, Child Welfare Department Reports (Box 9)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, Committee on Food Supply, Reports (Box 9)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, Committee on State Protection, Reports (Box 9)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, Committee on Finance Reports (Box 9)
      - C10: Connecticut Council of Defense, Committee on Americanization (Box 9)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, Fuel office (T.W. Russell) Reports (Box 9)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, Fuel Conservation Committee (Reports) (Box 9)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council, Committee on Publicity Reports (Box 9)
      - -----: Howard A. Lawrence [Correspondence] (Box 9)
      - C10: Connecticut Council of Defense, Health and Recreation Bureau [Reports] (Box 10)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, Committee on Education, Reports (Box 10)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, Committee on Sanitation and Medicine Reports (Box 10)
      - C10: Connecticut Council of Defense, Historical Records Department Reports (Box 10)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, Industrial Survey Committee Reports (Box 10)
      - C10: Connecticut Council of Defense, legal Committee, Reports (Box 10)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, Committee on Coordination of Societies Reports (Box 10)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, Commercial Relations Committee, Report (Box 10)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, Military and Naval Committee, Reports (Box 10)
      - C10: Connecticut Council of Defense, Non-war Construction Department, Reports (Box 10)
      - C10: Connecticut Council of Defense, Smileage Book Campaign, Reports (Box 10)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, Committee on Transportation, Reports (Box 10)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, Committee on War Savings [Reports] (Box 10)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, County Auxiliary Committees - Hartford Co., Reports (Box 11)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, County Auxiliary Committees - Fairfield Co., Reports (Box 11)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, County Auxiliary Committees - Litchfield Co., Reports (Box 11)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, County Auxiliary Committees - Middlesex Co., Reports (Box 11)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, County Auxiliary Committees - New Haven County, Reports (Box 11)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, County Auxiliary Committees - New London County, Reports (Box 11)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, County Auxiliary Committees - Tolland Co., Reports (Box 11)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, County Auxiliary Committees - Windham County, Reports (Box 11)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense (Special Committees) Office Systems and Accounts, Reports (Box 11)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense (Special Committees) Organization Committee - Reports (Box 11)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, Special Committee For Recruiting National Guard - Reports (Box 11)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense (Special Committee), Headquarters Committee (Box 11)
      - C10: Connecticut State Council of Defense, Committee on Manpower and Labor, Reports (Box 11)
      - C10.1: Summary of Reports, etc. (Box 11)
      - C11: Budget Committee Folder (Box 11)
      - C11: Finance (Council), Treasurer’s Office Data, etc. (Box 11)
      - C11: Secretary’s Office - Expenditures (Box 11)
      - C12: [Office Systems and Accounts] (Box 11)
      - C13: [Office Methods - Filing, etc.] (Box 11)
      - C14: Office Supplies & Equipment (Box 11)
      - C14.1: Purchasing of Supplies (Box 11)
      - C14.21a: Automobile Supplies (Box 12)
      - C14.21c: Card Records (Box 12)
      - C14.21d: Dictograph - Ediphone (Box 12)
      - C14.21f: Filing Equipment - Letter Trays, etc. (Box 12)
      - C14.21f: Flags (Box 12)
      - C14.21i: Index System (Box 12)
      - C14.21i: Inks (Box 12)
      - C14.21m: Mechanical Devices (Box 12)
      - C14.21p: Paper (Stationary), Cards, Printing Papers (Box 12)
      - C14.21p: Photo Engraving (Box 12)
      - C14.21p: Printing (Box 12)
      - C14.21s: Safes (Box 12)
      - C14.21s: Slides for Moving Pictures (Box 12)
      - C14.21w: White Pine (Box 12)
      - C14.21z: Other Supplies (Box 12)
      - C14.22: Quotations of Prices (Box 12)
      - C15: Automobile (Box 12)
      - C16: Mailing Department (Box 12)
      - C17: Requisitions (Box 12)
      - C18: Time Sheets (Box 12)
      - C19: Badges of Council (Box 12)
      - C20: Telegrams and Telephone (Box 12)
      - C24: Volunteer Workers (Box 13)
      - C24: Volunteered Assistance (Application for Work) (Box 13)
      - C25: Recommendations (Box 13)
      - C50: Reconstruction Work - Future of State Council System (Box 13)
      - C902: How to Address other State Councils (Box 13)
      - C902: [Circular - Council of National Defense, Field Division] (Box 13)
      - C902: State Councils of Defense - Organization, Activities, etc. (Box 13)
      - C902.03: [Correspondence Re State Councils of Defense] (Box 13)
      - C902.04: [State Councils of Defense - Suggested Activities] (Box 13)
      - C902.11: Expenditures of other State Councils (Box 13)
      - C904: Alabama (Box 13)
      - C904: Arizona Council of Defense (Box 13)
      - C906.05: Arkansas - Press Bulletin (Box 13)
      - C907: California State Council (Box 13)
      - C907.08: California State Council of Defense-Circular Letters (Box 13)
      - C908: Colorado (Box 13)
      - C908.05: Colorado Weekly News Letter (Box 14)
      - C909: Delaware (Box 14)
      - C910.06: Florida (Box 14)
      - C912.05: Idaho State Council - Press Bulletins (Box 14)
      - C913.05: Illinois - Press Bulletins and Circulars (Box 14)
      - C913.05: Illinois - State Council News (Box 14)
      - C914.05: Indiana (Box 14)
      - C914.06: Indiana War Conference (Box 14)
      - C915.05: Iowa Council of Defense - Press Clip Sheets (Box 14)
      - C915.07: Iowa Council of Defense - Addresses, Speeches, etc. (Box 14)
      - C915.08: Iowa Council of Defense - Resolutions, etc. (Box 14)
      - C915.08: Iowa Council of Defense - Circular Letters (Box 14)
      - C917.06: Kentucky (Box 14)
      - C918: Louisiana (Box 14)
      - C919: Maine (Box 14)
      - C920: Maryland (Box 14)
      - C921: Massachusetts (Box 14)
      - C923.05: Minnesota in the War (Box 14)
      - C925: Missouri Council of Defense (Box 14)
      - C929: New Hampshire (Box 14)
      - C930: New Jersey (Box 15)
      - C931: New Mexico (Box 15)
      - C931.05: New Mexico War News (Box 15)
      - C932: New York (State) Council of Defense (Box 15)
      - C933: North Carolina Council (Box 15)
      - C934: North Dakota (Box 15)
      - C935.05: Ohio - Press Bulletins (Box 15)
      - C936.05: Oklahoma Press Bulletins (Box 15)
      - C936.05: Oklahoma State Council - Sooners in the War (Box 15)
      - C938: Pennsylvania Committee of Public Safety (Box 15)
      - C938.05: Pennsylvania Committee of Public Safety - Press Information (Box 15)
      - C940: South Carolina (Box 15)
      - C941: South Dakota (Box 16)
      - C941.05: South Dakota, Council of Defense (Box 16)
      - C943: Texas State Council of Defiance (Box 16)
      - C944: Utah (Box 16)
      - C945: Vermont (Box 16)
      - C945.05: Vermont Committee of Public Safety - Circulars (Box 16)
      - C948: West Virginia (Box 16)
      - C949: Wisconsin (Box 16)
      - C949.05: Wisconsin State Council - Forward (Box 16)
      - C950.05: Wyoming State Council - Press Notices (Box 16)
    - D. Finance (Box 16)
      - D14: Federal Reserve (Box 16)
      - D14.01: Capital Issues Committee (Box 16)
      - D15: Liberty Bonds (Box 16)
      - D16: First Liberty Loan (Box 16)
      - D17: Second Liberty Loan (Box 16)
      - D17: Second Liberty Loan - Lists, etc. (Box 16)
      - D17: Second Liberty Loan and Fairfield County Situation (Box 16)
      - D18: Third Liberty Loan (Box 16)
      - D18: Letter of April 24 Requesting Reading of Governor’s Liberty Loan Proclamation in the Churches (Box 16)
      - D19: Fourth Liberty Loan (Box 16)
      - D50: Securities (Box 16)
      - D50.1: Correspondence re Issuing of $100 Notes of Connecticut Power Co. (Box 16)
    - E. Publicity (Box 17)
      - E: Publicity (Box 17)
      - E01: Publicity Committees - Organization, etc. (Box 17)
      - E06: Committee on Publicity - Meetings (Box 17)
      - E10: Budget & Expense Memoranda (Box 17)
      - E14: Patriotism (Box 17)
      - E16: [Flag Day Program for Industrial Plants] (Box 17)
      - E17: Memorial day, 1918 May 30 (Box 17)
      - E18: Fourth of July Letters (Box 17)
      - E18: Fourth of July (Box 17)
      - E18.1: Fourth of July, 1918 (Box 17)
      - E18.2: Bastille Day (Box 17)
      - E18.3: [Labor Day] (Box 17)
      - E18.4: [Thanksgiving Day], 1918 (Box 17)
      - E18.5: Britain Day (Box 17)
      - E20: Bulletin Boards (Box 17)
      - E20: Correspondence A-D, Orders For Bulletin Boards, Sign Strips, and Posters (Box 17)
      - E20: Correspondence E-Z, Orders For Bulletin Board, etc. (Box 18)
      - E20: Postal Cards re Bulletin Boards (Box 18)
      - E20: Correspondence with Town Committees re Orders for Bulletin Boards and Posters (Arranged by Town Alphabetically, Dead Correspondence), 1917 (Box 18)